http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/05/07/antibiotic-resistance-software_n_7228766.html 
 
In our selected article, the author summarizes a recent study in which researchers attempt to reverse the evolution of antibiotic resistance in bacteria by using data to mathematically determine optimized treatment plans.  Since the advent of antibiotics, bacteria have been adapting to normal treatment regimens. Antimicrobial resistant bacteria (aka, superbugs), currently account for 700,000 deaths annually but this number could increase to 10 million by 2050 due to further bacterial adaptation. 

In the research work cited in the article, the researchers presuppose that resistance of bacteria to antibiotics is unavoidable, and thus present a novel method to optimize the standard treatment regimen. Currently, most doctors use a trial and error method  when prescribing antibiotics. The researchers, aiming to improve this approach, developed a mathematical model to optimize antibiotic selection. They bred multiple genotypes of E. coli in order to mimic stages of evolutionary resistance and subsequently performed an algorithmic search through the results of multiple treatments to identify the treatment paths that had the highest probability for counteracting the evolutionary resistance of each genotype. 

Even though this study involves a clever application of mathematic and data-scientific principles, its current utility is questionable. Since it is a highly controlled experiment, its application to the real world is suspect. While the work described in this research article is seemingly of high quality as evidenced by its publication in reputed journal[1][2][3], it is proposed that for increasing its utility for pragmatic use that the following issues be addressed. One, bacterial or microbial colonies are never homogeneous, which the study uses as a basis.  Inter-microbe interaction that leads to stronger defenses to antibiotics must be a relevant part of future studies for they will almost certainly skew the growth rates and reversal rates. Also, the strain of E. coli used, doesn’t even cause disease. Two, the ambient, biological and chemical environment in which the results were generated are significantly simpler than with a human body or hospital situation where a microbe colony typically thrives and must be factored in. Third, microbes tend to react to antibiotic stimuli in ways that is not predictable in 24 hours terms, a term to which the research was limited. Over a period of a few days, microbes tend to find ways of reversing initial effects, including mutation over multi-day terms, a term that was not studied. Fourth, the use empirical result or probability-based results as a prescription technique are black box style results and need corroboration through further study. A patient or doctor might have difficulty accepting this prescription style over the current method founded in medical expertise. 
 
References 
1. http://www.bbc.com/news/health-30416844
2. http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0122283 
3. http://www.pharmaceutical-journal.com/news-and-analysis/research-briefing/mathematical-model-calculates-odds-of-resistance-developing-during-antibiotic-treatment/20068548.article, Pharmaceutical Journal, 2015. 
